<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Genome Informatics</title>
    <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Genome Informatics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>(c) 2018 Copyright Genome Informatics University of Duisburg Essen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 19:39:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://rahmannlab.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to Github</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2018/08/moving-to-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 19:39:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2018/08/moving-to-github/</guid>
      <description>From now on the website of our reasearch group is online at https://rahmannlab.github.io . The content is rendered using Hugo on Travis-CI or locally.
Source code of newly developed programs will be part of our Github group github.com/rahmannlab. Old projects are mainly located at bitbucket.org/genomeinformatics and will be maintained there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo Port</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2018/08/porting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 15:21:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2018/08/porting/</guid>
      <description>Porting to Hugo The research group around Sven Rahmann upgrades the website from WordPress to Hugo. See how easy this will be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/people/</guid>
      <description>People The group has offices in both Essen and Dortmund.
 Essen:  Group members can be reached by email using the address Firstname.Lastname@uni-due.de. The location V183 refers to Virchowstr. 183, 45147 Essen. The phone number prefix is +49 (201) 723-xxxx.  Dortmund:  Group members can be reached by email using the address Firstname.Lastname@tu-dortmund.de. The location OH14 refers to Otto-Hahn-Str. 14, 44227 Dortmund. The phone number prefix is +49 (231) 755-xxxx.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>projects This page lists the current projects topics of the group.
See also the Software page for publicly available Software.
Current Projects Metatranscriptome Analysis
Daniela Beisser &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with the Biodiversity group (Jens Boenigk), Essen
Protein Hypernetworks
Bianca Stöcker, Johannes Köster &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with Eli Zamir (MPI Stuttgart)
Analysis of ddRAD sequencing data with error-tolerant hashing
Henning Timm &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with AG Aquatische Ökosystemforschung (Florian Leese), Essen</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YeastScent: Volatile metabolites as quantitative proxy for metabolic network operation of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/yeastscent/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2017 10:21:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/yeastscent/</guid>
      <description>Elias Kuthe &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
For rapid yeast production, the optimal feed rate is crucial: If too little glucose is provided, growth rate is not optimal. On the other hand, too much glucose leads to the so called crabtree effect where ethanol is produced, which leads to low-quality yeast or even to a lost batch.
In this project, we therefore aim to better understand the changes in metabolism during yeast fermentation just before the onset of ethanol production by monitoring volatile organic compounds (VOCs) measured by multi-capillary column ion mobility spectrometry (MCC/IMS).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OsteoSys: Osteoporose ‐ eine Volkserkrankung im Kontext von kardiovaskulären Komplikationen und chronischer lnflammation: systemmedizinischer Ansatz zur personalisierten Therapie</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/osteosys/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 11:36:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/osteosys/</guid>
      <description>**Felix Mölder &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with Marien Hospital Herne, St. Anna Hospital Herne,
Ruhr-University Bochum, Frauenhofer-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der
angewandten Forschung e.V., Beckman Coulter**
Osteoporosis is a disease in which reduced bone strength leads to a high risk of fractures. With more than 6 million affected patients in Germany, it is already seen as a national disease today. However, through demographic change, the number of affected people is constantly increasing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynatrait</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/dynatrait/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 09:14:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/dynatrait/</guid>
      <description>**Daniela Beisser, Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with the Jens Boenigk and Christina Bock (Biodiversity, Essen), Bernd Sures (Biodiversity, Essen) and Matthijs Vos (Theoretical and Applied Biodiversity, Bochum)**
We are part of the DFG Priority Programme (Schwerpunktprogramm 1704)
Flexibility matters: Interplay between trait diversity and ecological dynamics using aquatic communities as model systems (Dynatrait)

Our subproject &amp;#8220;Flexible until it snaps: Dynamics of genes &amp;amp; traits, densities &amp;amp; diversity in communities challenged</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metatranscriptome Analysis</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/metatranscriptome-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 08:28:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/metatranscriptome-analysis/</guid>
      <description>**Daniela Beisser, Sven Rahmann,
in collaboration with the Biodiversity, Essen**
Next generation sequencing technologies are increasingly applied to analyse complex ecosystems by mRNA sequencing of whole communities. In principal, each sequenced mRNA allows an assignment of the underlying species as well as a functional annotation. While the functional information is sufficiently covered by databases such as Uniprot and NCBI the approach is currently limited by incomplete taxonomic references.

For an accurate assignment of taxonomic groups to environmental metatranscriptomic reads we build a custom database that comprises all major eukaryotic groups and a stand-alone tool to assign reads with a low false discovery rate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exome Analysis</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/exome-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2016 13:09:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/exome-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Exomate is an exome-sequencing pipeline with a web frontend. It automates most steps needed to go from FASTQ files to variant calls, puts the calls and metadata about patients, samples, etc. into a database and then allows interactive analysis via a web frontend. It is primarily designed for easy use and has already been used in various studies [1,2,3].
&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;
A central postgresql database stores all information and statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subsequence combinatorics</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/subsequence-combinatorics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 19:34:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/subsequence-combinatorics/</guid>
      <description>Sven Rahmann
joint work with Cees Elzinga and Hui Wang
We have investigated several combinatorial problems (enumeration problems) related to subsequences within a sequence.
A subsequence is obtained from a string by deleting any number of characters; thus in contrast to a substring, a subsequence is not necessarily a contiguous part of the string. Counting subsequences under various constraints has become relevant to biological sequence analysis, to machine learning, to the analysis of categorical time series in the social sciences, and to the theory of word complexity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Arithmetic Automata (PAAs)</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/probabilistic-arithmetic-automata-paas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 19:26:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/probabilistic-arithmetic-automata-paas/</guid>
      <description>Tobias Marschall &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
Probabilistic Arithmetic Automata are an extension of Deterministic Finite Automata (DFAs) and Hidden Markov Models (HMMs) to allow (arithmetic or arbitrary binary) operations. Exact state-value probability distributions can be efficiently computed with in this framework, and many applications in string algorithmics and computational biology can be modeled in this framework and treated in a unifying manner. We have done work on
 Development of the PAA framework  CPM&amp;#8217;08 paper  Application: Exact analysis of pattern matching algorithms, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>q-unique sequences</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/q-unique-sequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 18:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/q-unique-sequences/</guid>
      <description>Marianna D&amp;#8217;Addario &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
Design of q-unique DNA sequences DNA nanoarchitechtures require carefully designed oligonucleotides with certain non-hybridization guarantees, which can be formalized as the q-uniqueness property on the sequence level. The challenge is to find a longest q-unique DNA sequence. This can be achieved by finding an Euler tour within the quotient graph of the De Bruijn graph (DBQG). For even q, self-complementary edges complicate the problem, and the graph has to be eulerized by deleting a minimum number of edges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whole Genome Methylation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/whole-genome-methylation-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 18:43:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/whole-genome-methylation-analysis/</guid>
      <description>**Christopher Schröder &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
in collaboration with the Institute of Human Genetics, Essen**
The Chair of Genome Informatics in cooperation with the Institue of Humen Genetics is part of the &amp;#8216;German Epigenome Programme&amp;#8217; (DEEP). The project focuses on the analysis of cells connected to complex diseases with high socio-economic impact. DEEP contributes innovative epigenome research data to the ‘International Human Epigenome Consortium’ (IHEC) by generating and interpreting up to 80 reference epigenomes of selected human cells and tissues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Library complexity and duplication rate estimation</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/library-complexity-and-duplication-rate-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 18:39:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/library-complexity-and-duplication-rate-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Christopher Schröder, Sven Rahmann  In high-throughput sequencing (HTS) projects, the sequenced fragments’ duplicate rate is a key quality metric. A high duplicate rate may arise from a low amount of input DNA and many PCR cycles. Many methods for downstream analyses require that duplicates be removed. If the duplicate rate is high, most of the sequencing effort and money spent would have been in vain. Therefore, it is of considerable interest to estimate the duplicate rate after sequencing only a small subsample at low depth (multiplexed with other libraries) for quality control before running the full experiment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of ddRAD-seq data with error tolerant hashing</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/analysis-of-ddrad-seq-data-with-error-tolerant-hashing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 16:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/analysis-of-ddrad-seq-data-with-error-tolerant-hashing/</guid>
      <description>Henning Timm, Sven Rahmann, in collaboration with AG Aquatische Ökosystemforschung, Essen
What is ddRAD-seq?  Double digest sequencing of restriction site associated DNA (ddRAD-seq) is used in population genomics in order to reduce the complexity of genomic data for inter- and intra-population analysis. The genetic diversity, meaning the abundance of different mutations in a population, can give insight into the quality of the habitat.
For example, if the diversity of two populations differs, this might be a sign for a stressor affecting one of the populations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25.04.2016 | Publication: SimLoRD – Simulation of Long Read Data</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2016/04/25/25-04-2016-publication-simlord-simulation-of-long-read-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 13:09:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/2016/04/25/25-04-2016-publication-simlord-simulation-of-long-read-data/</guid>
      <description>Bianca Stöcker; Johannes Köster; Sven Rahmann
Bioinformatics 2016;
10.1093/bioinformatics/btw286
SimLoRD is a read simulator for third generation sequencing reads and is currently focused on the Pacific Biosciences SMRT error model.
Third generation sequencing methods provide longer reads than second generation methods and have distinct error characteristics.
In a SMRT library the sequenced DNA fragments are circular with adapter sequences between forward and backward strand, and a fragment may be sequenced multiple times in a single run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elias Kuthe</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/elias-kuthe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 14:47:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/elias-kuthe/</guid>
      <description>   Büro   Virchowstr. 183, 1.OG,
Raum 1.09     Postadresse   Elias Kuthe
Genominformatik, Inst. für Humangenetik
Medizinische Fakultät
Universität Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55
45122 Essen    Telefon   +49 201 723-4045    E-Mail   elias.kuthe@tu-dortmund.de    WWW   https://bitbucket.org/eqt/     </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Felix Mölder</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/felix-moelder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 14:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/felix-moelder/</guid>
      <description>Büro   Virchowstr. 183, 1. OG, Raum 1.08a    Postadresse   Felix Mölder
Genominformatik, Inst. für HumangenetikMedizinische Fakultät
Universität Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55
45122 Essen     Telefon   +49 201 723-4045    E-Mail   felix.moelder[at]tu-dortmund.de    WWW   https://bitbucket.org/FeMoe/    I am a research assistant in Prof. Sven Rahmanns group, Chair of Genome Informatics, University Duisburg-Essen, Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marianna D’Addario</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/marianna-daddario/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 15:33:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/marianna-daddario/</guid>
      <description>
   Büro   Raum 215 Otto-Hahn-Str. 14
44227 Dortmund    Postadresse   Technische Universität Dortmund
Department of Computer Science
Chair of Algorithm Engineering (LS11)
Otto-Hahn-Str. 14
44227 Dortmund
Germany     Telefon   +49 231 755 7745    E-Mail   vorname.nachname@tu-dortmund.de    WWW   ls11-www.cs.uni-dortmund.de/staff/daddario     &amp;lt;div style=&amp;quot;clear: right;&amp;quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Henning Timm</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/henning-timm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 15:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/henning-timm/</guid>
      <description>   Büro   Room 1.09, Virchowstr. 183, 45147 Essen    Postadresse   Genome Informatics (Chair)
Faculty of Medicine, Institute of Human Genetics
University of Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55, 45122 Essen, Germany
    Telefon   +49 201 723-4046    E-Mail   henning.timm@tu-dortmund.de    WWW   https://henningtimm.gitlab.io      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daniela Beißer</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/daniela-beisser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 15:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/daniela-beisser/</guid>
      <description>I am a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Genome Informatics headed by Sven Rahmann at the University of Duisburg-Essen, Germany. I am working as a bioinformatician with a focus on next-generation sequencing analysis. My current projects include the detection of structural variants in damaged genomes, functional and taxonomic assessment in metatranscriptome sequencing data and the analysis of new pathogens by assembling the genome and transcriptome. Furthermore, I am working on methods for integrated network analysis using different *omics datasets in conjunction with biological networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bianca Stöcker</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/bianca-stoecker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 15:24:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/bianca-stoecker/</guid>
      <description>Büro   Virchowstr. 183, 1.OG,
Raum 1.09     Postadresse   Bianca Stöcker
Genominformatik, Inst. für Humangenetik
Medizinische Fakultät
Universität Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55
45122 Essen    Telefon   +49 201 723-4046    E-Mail   bianca.stoecker[at]tu-dortmund.de    WWW   #     I am working as PhD student in Prof. Sven Rahmanns group, Chair of Genome Informatics, University Duisburg-Essen, Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christopher Schröder</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/christopher-schroeder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2016 10:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/christopher-schroeder/</guid>
      <description>Büro   Virchowstr. 183, 1.OG,
Raum 1.09    Postadresse   Christopher Schröder
Genominformatik, Inst. für Humangenetik
Medizinische Fakultät
Universität Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55
45122 Essen    Telefon   +49 201 723-4045    E-Mail   christopher.schroeder[$]tu-dortmund.de    WWW   http://christopherschroeder.bitbucket.io    I am a computer scientist with a focus on algorithm engineering and data analysis in bioinformatics, specialized on exome and whole-genome bisulphite (WGBS) data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sven Rahmann</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/sven-rahmann/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 10:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/group/sven-rahmann/</guid>
      <description>Contact Details     Essen   Dortmund     Büro   Virchowstr. 183,
1.OG, Raum 1.10   Otto-Hahn-Str. 14
2. OG, Raum 2.14    Postadresse  Prof. Dr. Sven Rahmann
Genominformatik, Inst. für Humangenetik
Medizinische Fakultät
Universität Duisburg-Essen
Hufelandstr. 55
45147 Essen  Prof. Dr. Sven Rahmann
Bioinformatik
Informatik XI
TU Dortmund
44221 Dortmund    Telefon  +49 201 723-404  +49 231 755-7701     E-mail   Sven.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small RNA Sequencing</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/small-rna-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 11:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/small-rna-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>This website contains material on the analysis of small RNA, in particular miRNA, sequencing experiments. It refers to
 a submitted manuscript &amp;#8220;Identifying Transcriptional miRNA Biomarkers by Integrating High-Throughput Sequencing and Real-Time PCR Data&amp;#8221; the paper Deep sequencing reveals differential expression of microRNAs in favorable versus unfavorable neuroblastoma by Schulte et al (2010).  Supplementary Material for &amp;#8220;Identifying Transcriptional miRNA Biomarkers by Integrating High-Throughput Sequencing and Real-Time PCR Data&amp;#8221;  Accompanying Sotware We provide a zip archive normalize-mirna-expression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protein Hypernetworks</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/protein-hypernetworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 11:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/protein-hypernetworks/</guid>
      <description>**Bianca Stöcker, Johannes Köster &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann,
collaboration with Eli Zamir (MPI Dortmund)**
   Protein interactions are fundamental building blocks of biochemical reaction systems underlying cellular functions. The complexity and functionality of such systems emerge not from the protein interactions themselves but from the dependencies between these interactions. Therefore, a comprehensive approach for integrating and using information about such dependencies is required.
We present an approach for endowing protein networks with interaction dependencies using propositional logic, thereby obtaining protein hypernetworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DNA Motif Discovery</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/motif-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 11:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/motif-discovery/</guid>
      <description>Tobias Marschall &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann

The motif discovery problem consists of finding over-represented patterns in a collection of biosequences. It is one of the classical sequence analysis problems, but still has not been satisfactorily solved in an exact and efficient manner. This is partly due to the large number of possibilities of defining the motif search space and the notion of over-representation. Even for well-defined formalizations, the problem is frequently solved in an ad hoc manner with heuristics that do not guarantee to find the best motif.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microarray Design and Layout</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/microarray-design-and-layout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 11:22:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/microarray-design-and-layout/</guid>
      <description>Sergio A. de Carvalho Jr. &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
Oligonucleotide microarrays consist of small DNA fragments (probes) chemically synthesized at specific locations (spots) of a solid surface. Probes are typically 25 to 60 nucleotides long and are synthesized in parallel, in a series of repetitive steps. Each step appends a particular nucleotide to selected regions of the chip. Selection occurs by exposure to light with the help of a photolithographic mask or micromirror arrays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of ion mobility spectroscopy data with restricted resources</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/ion-mobility-spectroscopy-ims-analysis-with-restricted-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 11:16:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/ion-mobility-spectroscopy-ims-analysis-with-restricted-resources/</guid>
      <description>**Dominik Kopczynski, Marianna D&amp;#8217;Addario &amp;amp; Sven Rahmann
(Project TB1, SFB 876)**
Ion mobility spectrometry measures ion intensity S(r,t) of a mixture of molecules after a certain retention time r in a separation phase and a certain drift time t (&amp;#8220;inverse ion mobility&amp;#8221;) in the spectrometer. Different molecules generally lead to distinct peaks in the intensity signal; so it is theoretically possible to identify and quantify a number of different metabolites, for example in exhaled human breath.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Pattern Matching Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/analysis-of-pattern-matching-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 10:52:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/projects/analysis-of-pattern-matching-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>We propose a framework for the exact probabilistic analysis of window-based pattern matching algorithms, such as Boyer-Moore, Horspool, Backward DAWG Matching, Backward Oracle Matching, and more.
In particular, we show how to efficiently obtain the distribution of such an algorithm&amp;#8217;s running time cost for any given pattern in a random text model, which can be quite general, from simple uniform models to higher-order Markov models or hidden Markov models (HMMs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lehre</title>
      <link>https://rahmannlab.github.io/lehre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 09:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rahmannlab.github.io/lehre/</guid>
      <description>Prof. Rahmann bietet UA-Ruhr-weit Bioinformatik-Veranstaltungen an, insbesondere in den Informatik-Studiengängen der TU Dortmund, sowie im Studiengang &amp;#8220;Angewandte Informatik&amp;#8221; der RUB.
Allgemeines  Lehrmaterial (Skripte, etc.) Wichtige Hinweise zu allen Lehrveranstaltungen, Prüfungen, etc.! Abschlussarbeiten (Bachelor, Diplom, Master)  Aktuell: Sommersemester 2017  Computational Omics (2V+2Pr; 6 LP); Master-Vertiefungsmodul PG 605 &amp;#8220;PanGeA &amp;#8211; Effiziente Datenstrukturen für Pan-Genom-Annotationen&amp;#8221;, Phase I (8 Pr; 10 LP), wird im WS 2017/18 fortgesetzt (nur nach Anmeldung) Betreuung von Abschlussarbeiten (Bachelor-, Master-, Diplom-, sowie Doktorarbeiten), inkl.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>